Finding Aid for Washtenaw County Community Mental Health Center. Substance Abuse Coordinating Agency Records, 1970-1988
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Washtenaw County Community Mental Health Center. Substance Abuse Coordinating Agency 1970-1988
Washtenaw County Community Mental Health Center. Substance Abuse Coordinating Agency.
16.75 linear feet
90181 Bf 2
Records documenting coordination of substance abuse prevention and treatment efforts in Washtenaw and Livingston County, Michigan; subgroups include administrative files; records relating to the interaction of coordinating agency with direct care substance abuse services providers; collected materials pertaining to various professional and citizen advocacy groups concerned with the problem of substance abuse; and subject files.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were donated by the Washtenaw County Community Mental Health Center Substance Abuse Coordinating Agency (Donor No. 7691 ) in three accessions, June 1989, November 1989, and April 1990.
The record group is open to research.
The history of substance abuse coordination by the Washtenaw County Community Mental Health Center (WCCMHC) dates back to 1970 when the center received a mandate from the state to provide a coordination effort in drug programming for Washtenaw County. In 1971 the Office of Drug Program Coordination (ODPC) was established by the Center and the first Comprehensive Drug Plan for Washtenaw County was drafted.
Coordination of substance abuse services received its current legislative mandate by Public Act 56 (PA 56) of the Michigan Public Health Acts of 1973. Prior to this time, agencies were classified as dealing with either alcohol or drug problems. PA 56 combined all of these agencies into one coordination system under the direction of the Office of Substance Abuse Services (OSAS). The Washtenaw County Community Mental Health Services Board (WCCMHSB) was initially designated the Substance Abuse Coordinating Agency for the county by the Washtenaw County Board of Commissioners in 1974, as authorized under PA 56. The redesignation of ODPC as the Office of Substance Abuse Coordination reflects the increased responsibilities under PA 56.
WCCMHC serves the following functions in order to fulfill the responsibilities of substance abuse coordination:
Development of a comprehensive county plan for substance abuse treatment, rehabilitation, and prevention services.
Collection and transfer of data from local licensed agencies.
Preparation and submission of an annual budget request for the allocation of state-administered substance abuse program funds.
Establishment of subcontracts with local agencies to provide direct services.
Regular evaluation of substance abuse services in the county.
Provision of technical assistance to local substance abuse service organizations.
These functions allow the Coordinating Agency to exert considerable control over county-wide priorities and budgets and some control over programming and policies by virtue of its role in the licensing process.
Community input regarding drug issues and services was provided through the Drug Advisory Council until 1975, when the council was reconstituted as the Substance Abuse Advisory Council (SAAC) in keeping with its new role under PA 56. The twenty-five citizen members provide community input directly to WCCMHSB by their review of the annual "Comprehensive Plan", and comments on substance abuse issues and the effectiveness of services.
In 1976 the Michigan Department of Public Health, in an effort to eliminate duplication and high administrative costs, consolidated the Livingston and Washtenaw County Coordinating Agencies. The consolidated Livingston-Washtenaw Substance Abuse Coordinating Agency is governed solely by the WCCMHSB. Input, direction and guidance are provided by the Bi-County SAAC, and by licensed substance abuse programs, local municipalities, and the general public. A forum is made available at regular Board meetings as well as regular meetings of the Advisory Council for input from all of the above-named groups.
The Washtenaw County Community Mental Health Center Substance Abuse Coordinating Agency (SACA) record group consists of materials from 1970 to 1988 which document the coordination of substance abuse prevention and treatment efforts in Washtenaw and Livingston counties. Overall strengths of the collection include materials which document the agency's approaches to management, credentialing, and funding, and the records of the Michigan Association of Substance Abuse Coordinators, a statewide network of coordinating agency administrators.
This record group can be studied to gain insight into the actual processes involved in coordinating a variety of local service provider agencies by SACA, which is in the middle echelon of the state substance abuse hierarchy. The researcher can also gain an understanding of how, and what types of information flow up and down that hierarchy. Agency functions, as listed previously in the History section, which are well documented are the development of comprehensive plans, review of license applications, and the preparation of annual budget requests.
This agency is the focal point for the allocation of federal and state funds for substance abuse in Washtenaw and Livingston Counties. The researcher can gain an understanding of the myriad types of substance abuse services local agencies provide, including prevention, casefinding, emergency care, intermediate care, inpatient care, outpatient care and rehabilitative/supportive care.
The record group consists of folders arranged alphabetically within four series. The Administrative Files and Agencies and Programs series have been maintained in their original order, while the Professional and Citizen Advocacy Groups and Topical Files series are artificial groupings created to facilitate order and access to the records.
Subjects:
Drug abuse--Michigan.; Livingston County (Mich.); Substance abuse--Michigan.; Washtenaw County (Mich.); Washtenaw County Community Mental Health Center. Substance Abuse Coordinating Agency.
- Administrative Files 1970-1988
  The Administrative Files series (8 linear feet) consists of materials, 1970-1988, that directly relate to the coordination of substance abuse prevention and treatment programs. Included are annual reports, correspondence, plans, contracts, budgets, directories of agencies, proposals, and reports.
  The researcher can get a basic introduction to the complex state substance abuse network by starting with the "History - Substance Abuse Coordination" folder in box one. An overview of how SACA operates can be discerned by reviewing the Comprehensive Plans and Annual Action Plans. The Comprehensive Plans, which end in 1978, document the early operations of the coordinating agency and contain budget summaries, definitions and provider agency information broken down by the type of service provided: prevention, casefinding or treatment. The Annual Action Plans follow chronologically after the Comprehensive Plans and, with the exception of fiscal year 1985/86, there is a complete run of these documents through 1987. Information in the annual plans is organized by agency names and gives an excellent overview of budgets, funding priorities and funded agencies.
  The most important function of the coordinating agency is its role in the funding process. The "funding" folders contain reports, proposals, correspondence, minutes, personal notes and statistics. These materials illustrate funding patterns and guidelines, as well as the actual process of making funding decisions.
  The researcher can investigate attempts to develop effective management techniques used in coordinating activities by examining the Integrated Substance Abuse Management Information System (ISAMIS), Management Information System (MIS), and Data Compact materials. ISAMIS was the first attempt by OSAS to develop a standardized statewide information system. Due to deficiencies perceived in the ISAMIS system, a Coordinating Agency Consortium was formed in 1977 to develop a more efficient system. This group eventually evolved into the Southeastern Michigan Data Compact, which became the basis for a statewide substance abuse database. The folders labeled "Documentation Flow Charts and Forms" in the MIS materials provide the researcher with insight into the nature of client documentation at various agencies. This information was used in a MIS revision and includes the types of data collected, how the paperwork flows through the pertinent organizations and time estimates for the various processes.
  The credentialing of substance abuse professionals in Michigan can be studied by referring to the "credentialing" folders. Materials relate to the development of the Apprentice Counselor Credential of the OSAS which began in December 1982 and the merging of this system with the existent Michigan Certification Board for Addiction Specialists system in 1984. The goals of credentialing are to assure minimum levels of knowledge among direct service staff and to recognize high levels of competency among counselors so that they can compete professionally with "degreed" individuals.
  The PA 339 materials illustrate the response of the substance abuse network to a piece of high impact legislation, in this case the Substance Abuse Assistance Act (Decriminalization of Public Intoxication). The researcher can trace the history of the committees which were formed and the procedures developed to effect a smooth transition to the new system.
  The complex issues involved in determining the degree of success treatment has achieved can be investigated in the Treatment Outcome Project folders, which contain reports, memos, correspondence, surveys, minutes, and a dissertation on factors in successful treatment. The focus of the project shifted away from determining client satisfaction to outcome assessment. Demand for data on the effectiveness of programs has arisen from consumer groups, legislators, insurance companies, and other funding sources. Resulting information has been used to monitor client outcome, assess program effectiveness, and as an aid in program planning.
  - History-Substance Abuse Coordination 1973-1976, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Advisory Commission on Substance Abuse Services-Michigan Department of Public Health 1979-1983, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Agency Descriptions 1974 (Box 1)
  - Alcohol Client Matching Project 1987 (Box 1)
  - Annual Action Plans
    - Fiscal Years 1979/80-1984/85, 18 folders (Box 1)
    - Fiscal Year 1986/87 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports 1975-1976 (Box 2)
  - Appeal Process 1975 (Box 2)
  - Audit 1978-1979 (Box 2)
  - Chemical Dependency Planning Committee 1982 (Box 2)
  - Communication Reports 1980-1983 (Box 2)
  - Comprehensive Plans 1971-1972, 1974-1978
    - Macomb County 1975 (Box 2)
    - Washtenaw County
      - Fiscal Year 1971/72, 3 folders (Box 2)
        (includes basic plan, grant application, and grant continuation)
      - Fiscal Year 1975/76, 3 folders (Box 2)
        (includes basic plan and grant materials)
      - Fiscal Year 1976/77 (Box 2)
      - Fiscal Year 1977/78 (Livingston and Washtenaw)
        - (Part 1) Assessment and Plan Updates (Box 2)
        - (Part 2) Proposed Prevention Programming (Box 2)
        - (Part 3) Proposed Casefinding Programming (Box 2)
        - (Part 4) Proposed Treatment/Rehabilitation Programming (Box 2)
        - (Part 5) Evaluation, 2 folders (Box 2)
        - (Part 6) Budget (Box 2)
        - (Part 7) Assessment update (Box 2)
        - (Part 8) Appendix and Fiscal Year 1978/79 budget estimate (Box 2)
      - Fiscal Year 1978/79 (Box 2)
  - Confidentiality 1973-1980 (Box 2)
  - Confidentiality Seminar 1978 (Box 2)
  - Consultation and Education Committee 1976-1977 (Box 2)
  - Contracts and Budgets-Fiscal Years 1976/77-1986/87, 10 folders (Box 3)
  - Coordinating Agencies-Michigan 1981, 1982, 1984 (Box 3)
  - Coordinating Agency Management Review 1984 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 1978-1988
    - All Licensed Programs 1980-1986, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Funded Programs 1978-1986, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - General 1978-1988, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Hospital Administrators 1982 (Box 3)
    - Internal 1980 (Box 3)
  - Credentialing 1978, 1980-1987
    - Board 1981-1987, 7 folders (Box 3)
    - Manuals 1978, 1980, 1983, 1986-1987 (Box 4)
    - Reports 1981, 1983-1987 (Box 4)
  - Department of Public Health
    - Audits 1976-1979 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence 1984-1985 (Box 4)
  - Designated Screening Agency 1983 (Box 4)
  - Detoxification Proposals 1973 (Box 4)
  - Directories, undated 1973-1974 (Box 4)
  - Drug Advisory Committee 1973-1974 (Box 4)
  - Evaluation Reports undated (Box 4)
  - Financial Composite Data 1979-1981 (Box 4)
  - Funding 1976-1986
    - Guidelines 1981-1983, 1986 (Box 4)
    - Patterns 1976-1985 (Box 4)
    - Process 1976-1986, 9 folders (Box 4)
    - Proposals 1981, 1983, 1986, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Hess, Thomas G. 1978 (Research and Evaluation) (Box 4)
  - Holiday Awareness Campaign 1983-1988, 2 folders (Box 4)
    (Say No to Drunk Driving)
  - Host/Party Tips 1985-1986 (Box 4)
  - Integrated Substance Abuse Management Information System (ISAMIS) 1975-1978
    - Correspondence 1975-1978 (Box 5)
    - Procedures 1975-1976 (Box 5)
    - Report 1975 (Box 5)
  - Job Descriptions, undated 1973, 1976, 1984 (Box 5)
  - Joint Commission on Accreditation of Hospitals (JCAH) 1982-1984, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Juvenile Court Services 1985-1986 (Box 5)
  - Licensing, undated 1977-1982 (scattered) (Box 5)
  - Livingston County-Correspondence and Information 1976-1982 (Box 5)
  - Livingston County Merger undated, 1976 (Box 5)
  - Long Range Target Strategy 1979-1982 (Box 5)
  - Management Information System (MIS) 1977-1978
    - Documentation Flow Charts and Forms 1977
      - (Part 1) Ann Arbor Program (Box 5)
      - (Part 2) Ypsilanti Area Community Services (YACS) (Box 5)
      - (Part 3) Out County (Box 5)
      - (Part 4) Court Services and Huron Valley Child Guidance Clinic (Box 5)
    - Instructions for Fiscal Year 1978/79 (Box 5)
    - "Management Information Analysis" (report) 1977 (Box 5)
    - "Management Information Needs of Mental Health Center Managers" (report) 1977 (Box 5)
    - Papers for the Evaluation Network Third Annual Conference 1977 (Box 5)
    - MIS revision 1977 (Box 5)
  - Medicaid Project, undated 1984 (Box 5)
  - Mental Health Board 1982-1983 (correspondence) (Box 5)
  - Michigan Department of Corrections 1988 (proposals), 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Michigan Legislature 1980-1987
    - Correspondence 1980, 1984 (Box 5)
    - Early Intervention for the Prevention of Juvenile Delinquency 1987 (Box 5)
    - Legislation Reviews 1981-1984 (Box 5)
    - Reports 1980-1984 (Box 5)
    - Special Committee on Substance Abuse 1980 (minutes) (Box 5)
  - Multi-media Show Information 1971 (Box 6)
  - National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA) 1975-1976, 1978 (correspondence) (Box 6)
  - Office of Substance Abuse Services (OSAS) 1976-1984
    - Correspondence 1978-1983
      - Administration Division 1979-1983, 5 folders (Box 6)
      - Evaluation and Data Services Division 1979-1982 (Box 6)
      - Licensing Division 1978-1983, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Operations Division 1979-1983, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Program Division 1979-1983, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - State Wide Services Contract 1978-1981 (scattered) (Box 6)
    - Follow Up Status Reports 1983 (Box 6)
    - "The Legal Drinking Age Issue" 1977 (report to Governor Milliken) (Box 6)
    - News Review 1978-1981 (Box 6)
    - Section 20 Review 1976 (reports) (Box 6)
    - Special Projects 1977-1984
      - Channel One Prevention Project 1980 (Box 6)
      - Data Compact 1977-1984, 8 folders (Box 6)
      - Parent/Family Prevention Project 1980-1981 (Box 7)
      - Program Evaluation Skills Training 1978, 1980 (Box 7)
      - Treatment Alternatives to Street Crime 1980 (Box 7)
      - Youth Drinking and Driving Prevention Project 1980 (Box 7)
      - Ypsilanti Southside Project 1979-1980 (Box 7)
    - Special Public Policy Reports 1979-1980 (Box 7)
  - Papers 1971-1973, 1977, 1980-1982, 1987
    - "Concept for the Development of a Client (Volunteer) Organization During Fiscal Year 82/83" 1982 (Box 7)
    - "Direct and Indirect Service Standards" 1977 (Box 7)
    - "Evaluation and Research in the Comprehensive Drug Program" 1971 (Box 7)
    - "Patterns of Drug Use in Four Michigan Secondary School Systems" 1972 (research paper) (Box 7)
    - "The Prevention Network in Michigan: Helping Volunteers Succeed" 1987 (proposal) (Box 7)
    - "Second Report on the Drug Counseling Program" 1973 (Skills Center and Community High School) (Box 7)
    - "Transitional Apartment Program" 1980 (report) (Box 7)
  - Personnel 1977-1980 (scattered) (Box 7)
  - Police Training Grant undated (Box 7)
  - Prevention Project 1976 (Box 7)
  - Prevention Training-Region V 1980-1981 (Box 7)
  - Proposals 1973, 1980, 1987-1988 (Box 7)
  - Public Act 339 1975-1979
    - Correspondence 1975-1979, 5 folders (Box 7)
    - Reports and Plans, undated 1976-1977 (Box 7)
    - Task Force 1976-1978 (Box 7)
  - Public Hearings 1976-1986 (scattered) (Box 7)
  - Quarterly Management Reports-Fiscal Years 1979/80-1984/85, 6 folders (Box 7)
  - Recipient Rights Information 1982, 1984 (Box 7)
  - Regional Therapeutic Community Program Proposal 1973 (Box 7)
  - State Evaluation Task Force 1977-1979 (Box 7)
  - State Prevention Advisory Committee-OSAS 1979-1983 (scattered) (Box 7)
  - Substance Abuse Advisory Council 1975-1985
    - General Information 1975-1985, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - "Handbook" 1981 (Box 8)
    - Minutes 1975-1981, 1984, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Substance Abuse Committee 1979, 1982, 1984-1985 (minutes) (Box 8)
  - Substance Abuse Needs Assessment 1985-1986 (Box 8)
  - Substance Abuse Presentations 1981 (Box 8)
  - Training 1975-1980 (scattered) (Box 8)
  - Treatment Outcome Project 1976-1980
    - Budget/Contract 1977-1978 (Box 8)
    - Client Episode Outcome Summary (CEOS)/Global Assessment Scale (GAS) Committee 1978-1979 (Box 8)
    - CEOS Redevelopment 1979 (Box 8)
    - Client Outcome Assessment Project 1976-1977 (funding proposal) (Box 8)
    - Client Satisfaction Survey (CSS) 1977 (Box 8)
    - CSS Summary Results 1977 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence 1976-1978 (Box 8)
    - "Factors in Successful Treatment Outcome in Community Mental Health" 1978 (dissertation by Lambert Maguire) (Box 8)
    - First Year Progress Report 1977 (Box 8)
    - Interrater Agreement-Training Tapes 1977 (Box 8)
    - Mate Role Problems 1977-1978 (Box 8)
    - Outcome Memos 1976-1978 (Box 8)
    - Reliability 1977-1980 (Box 8)
    - Reports 1977-1979, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Reports for Lansing 1977 (Box 8)
  - Treatment and Prevention of Drug Abuse Program 1974 (grant continuation) (Box 8)
  - Videotaping Procedures 1977-1978 (Box 8)
  - Volunteers In Service To America (VISTA), undated 1985 (Box 8)
  - Yarvis proposal 1970 (Box 8)
- Agencies and Programs 1971-1988
  The Agencies and Programs series (7 linear feet) contains materials from 1971 to 1988 which document the interaction of the Coordinating Agency with direct care substance abuse service providers within Livingston and Washtenaw counties. These materials are arranged alphabetically by program title and the majority of the records pertain to funded programs, and primarily consist of contracts and budgets, correspondence, licensing documents and review/audit records. Reports, manuals, plans and resource guides are also present in this series. The Ann Arbor Community Center, Child and Family Services, and the Washtenaw Council on Alcoholism are agencies about which there is fairly comprehensive documentation.
  The history of heroin treatment in Washtenaw County is illustrated through the records of three programs: Octagon House, the Community Mental Health Treatment Facility (CMHTF), and the Child and Family Services Drug Treatment Program. The Octagon House program began in 1971 supported by funding from a Law Enforcement Assistance Administration (LEAA) Grant. Octagon House became independent of the Mental Health Center in 1975 since the provisions of PA 56 require that an organization either serve a coordination function or provide direct services. A series of problems developed at the House including; noncompliance with state and federal regulations, financial irregularities, conflict of interest, and falsification of client records. These problems led to the closing of Octagon House and a waiver of the restrictions of PA 56 so that the coordinating agency could provide services to former clients of the House. Treatment was provided by the CMHTF program under the direction of SACA from July 1979 until April 1980, at which time Child and Family Services (CFS) was determined to be appropriate to administer the program. In June 1982 CFS renamed the program the Child and Family Services Drug Treatment Program.
  - Alcohol Abuse Prevention Program 1974-1981
    - Contracts and Budgets 1977-1981 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence 1976-1981, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - General Information 1975-1980 (Box 9)
    - Licensing 1974, 1976, 1979-1981 (Box 9)
  - Alcohol and Drug Abuse Services of Livingston County 1976-1984
    - Contracts and Budgets 1977-1983 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence 1977-1984, 4 folders (Box 9)
    - General Information 1978-1982 (Box 9)
    - Interim Agreement 1978-1979 (Box 9)
    - ISAMIS Reports 1976-1977 (Box 9)
    - Licensing 1983-1984, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Ann Arbor Community Center 1975-1988
    - Contracts and Budgets 1975-1983, 1987 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence 1977-1979, 1981-1988, 3 folders (Box 9)
    - General Information 1975-1982 (Box 9)
    - Licensing 1983-1985, 1987, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Monitoring Visits 1977 (Box 9)
    - Program Review/Record Audit 1975-1977 (Box 9)
    - Project Transition 1983 (Box 9)
  - Ann Arbor Consultation Services 1982-1984, 3 folders (Box 9)
  - Arbor Hills, P.C. 1985 (Box 9)
  - Assault Crisis Center, undated 1985 (Box 9)
  - A.W.M. Company 1978-1980 (Box 9)
  - Back Door Drop-In Center 1978-1988
    - Contracts and Budgets 1978-1983 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence 1978-1988, 3 folders (Box 9)
    - General Information 1978-1983, undated, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Licensing 1983-1986, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Beginning Alcohol and Addictions Basic Education Studies, (BABES) 1983-1985, 1987 (Box 10)
  - Beyer Memorial Hospital 1975-1987
    - Contracts and Budgets 1976-1983, 1987 (Box 10)
    - Correspondence 1978-1984 (Box 10)
    - General Information 1975-1981 (Box 10)
    - Licensing 1984-1987, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - The Blue Screw 1975 (methadone program) (Box 10)
  - Brighton Hospital Alcoholism Treatment Program 1976-1985
    - Correspondence 1977-1983 (Box 10)
    - Licensing 1976-1978, 1980-1985, 6 folders (Box 10)
  - Catherine McAuley Health Center 1979, 1981-1986
    - Alpha House 1982-1986
      - General Information 1982-1984 (Box 10)
      - Licensing 1985-1986, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Chemical Dependency Planning Committee 1979, 1981-1983 (Box 10)
    - Huron Oaks 1984-1986
      - General Information, undated 1986 (Box 10)
      - Licensing 1984-1986, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Intense Outpatient Program 1985 (Box 10)
  - Catholic Social Services of Washtenaw County 1974-1977 (Box 10)
  - Center for Counseling Services 1985 (Box 10)
  - Chelsea Community Hospital Alcoholism Therapy Program 1975-1985
    - Alcohol Therapy Manual undated (Box 11)
    - Contracts and Budgets 1975-1978 (Box 11)
    - Correspondence 1975, 1978-1981 (Box 11)
    - Kresge House 1979, 1985 (Box 11)
    - Licensing 1974-1985 (scattered), 4 folders (Box 11)
  - Child and Family Services 1971-1986
    - Contracts and Budgets 1977-1984 (scattered) (Box 11)
    - Correspondence 1978-1984, 2 folders (Box 11)